### **Manal Kamal Elzalabany**

elzalabany@demogr.mpg.de | website

#### **PROFESSIONAL PROFILE**

Manal K. Elzalabany is a multilingual epidemiologist & data analyst. She works currently as a project coordinator and researcher in MPIDR, and previously worked as a data analyst in WHO, and as a *Lancet*-associated researcher. Her research interests focus mainly on re/emerging infectious diseases & global health, using quantitative data methodologies. Manal holds an MSc Applied Statistics in Health Sciences program with Strathclyde university, 2024, and an MPH in Epidemiology & Biostatistics from the American University of Beirut, 2018. Manal is an expert user of R/RStudio, Rmarkdown & Quarto, and Shiny Web applications.

#### **EDUCATION**

### MSc | September 2022- September 2024 | Faculty of Science - University of Strathclyde

- · MSc Applied Statistics in Health Sciences Department of Mathematics & Statistics
- · Graduation project: Age-Period-Cohort analysis of Cervical Cancer in Scotland, 1997-2021

### MPH | August 2016- June 2018 | Faculty of Health Sciences- American University of Beirut

- · Master of Public Health in Epidemiology and Biostatistics, EPBS
- · Graduation project: Epidemiological Analysis of Leprosy in Egypt, 2008-2017

### BVSc | September 2004- May 2009 | Faculty of Veterinary Medicine- Cairo University

Bachelor degree in Veterinary Medical Sciences

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Research Associate | June 2022 - September 2024 | Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR)- Rostock, Germany

COVID-19 Data management & time series analysis in R, Shiny App development.

# Data Analyst | June 2021- May 2022 | World Health Organization-Eastern Mediterranean Regional Office – EMRO Cairo, Egypt

In Health Emergencies Programme (WHE), Country Emergency Preparedness and International Health Regulations (CPI) unit

COVID-19 survey data analysis in R, COVID-19 PHSM data analysis & visualization

# Epidemiologist | July 2020- June 2021 | World Health Organization-Eastern Mediterranean Regional Office - EMRO Cairo, Egypt

In Health Emergencies Programme (WHE), Health Information Management (HIM) unit

COVID-19 data management & analytics in R, COVID-19 & other infectious diseases Event based surveillance & risk assessment

### Researcher | March 2020- December 2020 | COVID-19 Dispersed Volunteer Research Network

ANES survey data analysis in R, COVID-19 systematic review

## Research Affiliate | January 2020- June 2020 | *The Lancet*-AUB Commission on Syria "Health in Conflict"

Multi-sector needs assessment (MSNA) household survey analysis in R

# Research Associate | October 2018- December 2019 | *The Lancet*-AUB Commission on Syria "Health in Conflict"

Scoping review, APHA poster preparation

### Intern | January 2018- April 2018 | World Health Organization-Egypt country office

Leprosy & Malaria data analysis & Leprosy active surveillance field work

# Graduate Research Assistant | June 2017- December 2017 | *The Lancet*-AUB Commission on Syria "Health in Conflict"

Syria related health qualitative data management

# **Veterinary Epidemiologist | January 2010- July 2016 | South Giza Veterinary Governmental Department**

Zoonotic diseases monitoring and vaccination

[Further details about work experience are mentioned at the end of the resume]

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Database management:** Microsoft Access

Data wrangling, analysis, and modeling: R, Stata, Python & SPSS

Spatial analysis: ArcGIS & R

**Data visualization:** Tableau software & Power Bi **Reference management:** Endnote software & Citavi

Writing & publishing: Microsoft Word, PowerPoint & Publisher

#### **LANGUAGES**

#### Arabic: Mother Tongue | English: Proficient | French: Proficient | German: Beginner

#### **AWARDS**

Full merit-based Research and Training on Tropical Diseases- TDR Scholarship for Masters in Public Health | September 2016- June 2018

#### **CERTIFICATES & TRAININGS**

 Introduction to Outbreak Analytics using R | November 2020: London School of Hygiene & Tropical Medicine (LSHTM)

- Geographic Information Systems (GIS) for Public Health | June 2020: Boston University School of Public Health
- · Attestation de réussite de DELF B2 | Septembre 2019: Institut Français de Caire- Egypte
- Monitoring & Evaluation Professional Diploma | September 2018- March 2019: School of Continuing Education- American University of Cairo

#### **EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES**

### M & E Assistant | Namaa' School for Sustainable Development | May 2012- December 2015

- Co-designing the curriculum of Namaa' school in 2012,2013 and 2014
- · Co-planning for school strategic direction for the next school in 2015
- · Documentation & Evaluation of the curriculum designing process
- Contributing to 10-years' evaluation of the school (2005-2015) conduct qualitative and quantitative analysis

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

ORCID No.: <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2686-8364">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2686-8364</a>

#### 2023

- **Elzalabany M. K.**, Kniffka M. S., Donzowa J., Schöley J., Acosta E., Riffe T. The COVerAGE-DB vaccination addon: A global database of age-harmonized COVID-19 vaccination time series. Population Association of America. 2023. <a href="https://events.rdmobile.com/Lists/Details/1725962">https://events.rdmobile.com/Lists/Details/1725962</a>
- · Nikoloski Z, Bain R, **Elzalabany M. K.**, Hanna P, Aynsley TR, Samhouri D, Menchini L, Kapil N, Gillespie A. Modelling COVID-19 vaccination status and adherence to public health and social measures, Eastern Mediterranean Region and Algeria. Bull World Health Organ. 2023 Feb 1;101(2):111–20. https://doi.org/10.2471%2FBLT.22.288655

#### 2022

- Elmahal, O., Abdullah, A., **Elzalabany, M. K.**, Samhouri, D., & Brennan, R. (2022). Public health emergency operation centers-PHEOCs: status, gaps, and areas for improvements in the Eastern Mediterranean Region (BMJ Global Health 20227:e008573).
- · Samhouri, D., Barry, J., Abdullah, A., **Elzalabany, M. K.**, & Brennan, R. (2022). Development of the WHO Eastern Mediterranean Region's travel measures platform during the COVID-19 pandemic: a novel regional approach and interface in implementing the International Health Regulations (2005) and exchanging information in real time. *WHO Weekly epidemiological record*, 5(97), 25-32. Online: <a href="https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/351505">https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/351505</a>
- Hasan Q, Elfakki E, Fahmy K, et al. (2022). Inequities in the deployment of COVID-19 vaccine in the WHO Eastern Mediterranean Region, 2020–2021 BMJ Global Health7:e008139. <u>Link</u> (*acknowledgement*)

#### 2021

Abouzeid, M., Elzalabany, M.K., Nuwayhid, I. et al. Conflict-related health research in Syria, 2011–2019: a scoping review for *The Lancet* - AUB Commission on Syria. Confl Health 15, 92 (2021). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13031-021-00384-3">https://doi.org/10.1186/s13031-021-00384-3</a>

#### 2020

- Krista Wollny, Carol Liu, Ghinwa El Hayek, Sameer Gopalani, Hanh Dung Dao, Katharine Fagan-Garcia, Luca Martial, Manal Elzalabany, Helen Piontkivska, Arianna Amit, Jovia Nierenberg, Louisa Smith, Anhvinh Doanvo, Angel Desai, Vladimir Teif, Maimuna Majumder. Time-associated clinical and epidemiological parameters characterising COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis. PROSPERO 2020 CRD42020177045 Available from: https://www.crd.york.ac.uk/prospero/display\_record.php?ID=CRD42020177045
- Abdul-Khalek, R., Kayyal, W., Akkawi, A. R., Almalla, M., Arif, K., Karroum, L. B., . . ., Elzalabany, M. K.,.. Jawad, M. (2020). Health-related articles on Syria before and after the start of armed conflict: a scoping review for *The Lancet*-American University of Beirut Commission on Syria. *Confl Health* 14, 73 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1186/s13031-020-00316-7.

#### 2019

• Lewison, G., Abouzeid, M., Sabouni, A., Elzalabany, M., Jabbour, S., & Sullivan, R. (2019). Identification of the research on warfare and health, 1946-2017. Paper presented at & published in 17th International Conference on Scientometrics & Informetrics (ISSI2019), Vol I, p. 271-282. <a href="http://www.issi-society.org/publications/issi-conference-proceedings/proceedings-of-issi-2019/">http://www.issi-society.org/publications/issi-conference-proceedings/proceedings-of-issi-2019/</a>

#### 2018

- · Sabouni, A., Abouzeid, M., **Elzalabany, M.**, Fardousi, N., Ghaddar, F., & Jabbour, S. (2018). Public health and war: A critical synthesis towards a new approach. *Poster presentation at the European Public Health Conference (EPHC), Slovenia*
- Abouzeid, M., Sabouni, A., Fardousi, N., Ghaddar, F., Elzalabany, M., Khrisht, G., . . . Jabbour, S. (2018). Is there a 'field' of health and armed conflict? Towards a sustained and expanded role for the global health community. Paper presented at the APHA 2018 Annual Meeting & Expo, San Diego. <a href="https://apha.confex.com/apha/2018/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/420147">https://apha.confex.com/apha/2018/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/420147</a>